♪In the face of turmoil♪
♪ดื่มน้ำค้างแข็ง♪
♪Your roots hold firmly♪
♪กำรากของท่านไว้แน่น♪
♪To this piece of land♪
♪แผ่นดินผืนนี้♪
♪Chasing after the waves♪
♪ไล่ตามคลื่น♪
♪My leaves flutter across♪
♪ใบไม้ของข้าพัดผ่าน♪
♪The horizon♪
♪ชายแดนหมื่นลี้♪
♪Gazing from afar♪
♪เหม่อมองกันแสนไกล♪
♪At the end of the world♪
♪สุดฟากฝั่งคือ♪
♪Is eternity♪
♪ชั่วฟ้าดินสลาย♪
♪When we meet and then part♪
♪เมื่อพบกันแล้วลาจาก♪
♪When we rely on each other and then drift apart♪
♪เมื่ออิงแอบแล้วห่างไป♪
♪I have never forgotten♪
♪ข้าไม่เคยลืม♪
♪As the glinting of swords cut♪
♪พรายเงาดาบแสงกระบี่♪
♪Through the mottled sky♪
♪วาดผ่านรอยด่างของท้องฟ้า♪
♪The falling dreams♪
♪ฝันที่ตกลง♪
♪Shatter in the wind♪
♪แหลกสลายกลางสายลม♪
♪As the wind breaks through the waves♪
♪ฝ่าลมโต้คลื่น♪
♪It watches thousands of sails cross♪
♪มองนาวานับพันข้ามฟาก♪
♪The vast land and the boundless sea♪
♪ทะเลทุ่งนาแปรเปลี่ยน♪
♪Armor and red robes flying high♪
♪ชุดทหาร ชุดสตรี ลอยฟ่อง♪
♪In the face of bitterness, intense emotions, and joyful adventure♪
♪เคยดื่มน้ำแข็ง โลหิตไม่เย็น ฝันที่จะท่องทุ่งเล่อโหยว♪
♪I only wish you to be by my side♪
♪ปรารถนาเพียงท่านอยู่ข้างกาย♪
♪Making the most of what life offers♪
♪ไม่ผิดต่อแสงวสันต์♪
♪Like towering trees with interconnected roots, I'll accompany you to the ends♪
♪ต้นไม้สูงเสียดฟ้า รากประสาน ท่องไปสุดหล้าเคียงท่าน♪
♪Watching fireflies land on our shoulders♪
♪ดูหิ่งห้อยเกาะบนไหล่เราสอง♪
♪No regrets, no doubts in this world♪
♪ไม่เสียใจในโลกีย์♪
=Wonderland of Love=
=พสุธารักเคียงใจ=
=Episode 25=
=ตอนที่ 25=
People have different aspirations.
คนเราอุดมการณ์ไม่เหมือนกัน
Some desire to dominate the world.
บางคนอยากมีอำนาจล้นฟ้า
But I only wish to keep my promise.
แต่ข้าเพียงอยากรักษาสัญญา
When the world is at peace,
รอแผ่นดินสงบ
I want to guard the border
ไปรักษาชายแดน
at Laolan Pass with you.
ที่ด่านเหลาหลันกับเจ้า
What if I don't want to go back to Laolan Pass with you?
หากข้าไม่เต็มใจ
I know I can't force you.
ข้ารู้ว่าข้าฝืนใจเจ้าไม่ได้
But I hope
แต่ข้าก็ยังหวังว่า
you can come with me
เจ้าจะไปพร้อมข้าได้
because I like you.
เพราะข้าพึงใจต่อเจ้า
Lord Qin, please go back.
อ๋องฉินเชิญกลับเถอะ
I've said everything
สิ่งที่ข้าอยากพูด
I wanted to say.
ก็พูดหมดแล้ว
Ying...
อาอิ๋ง
Please leave.
ท่านไปเถอะ
Since we can't convince each other,
ในเมื่อเราต่าง
let's take some time
อย่างนั้นก็ใช้เวลาสักพัก
to think about it.
คิดให้ดี ๆ เถอะ
♪Waiting for memories to shatter and sink♪
♪รอความทรงจำ แหลกละเอียดจมหาย♪
♪The emotional scars in your heart♪
♪ตกลงบนรอยด่างบนหัวใจเจ้า♪
I was wrong that day.
วันนั้นข้าไม่ดีเอง
I shouldn't have said those harsh words to you.
ข้าไม่ควรใช้อารมณ์กับเจ้า
But I understand your feelings.
แต่ข้าเข้าใจความคิดของเจ้า
You don't want to see me sacrifice my life
เพราะเจ้ารักและให้ความสำคัญกับข้า
for someone else
ถึงไม่อยากเห็นข้า
because you love me.
ใช้ชีวิตไปแลกคนอื่น
♪I long to return to the very first moment♪
♪รำลึกถึงความทรงจำในช่วงเวลาแรก♪
If our positions were reversed,
หากสถานการณ์ของเราในวันนั้นสลับกัน
I think I would do the same.
ข้าคิดว่าข้าก็คงทำเช่นนี้เหมือนกัน
What's the point
ตอนนี้พูดเรื่องพวกนี้
of saying these things now?
จะมีความหมายอะไรอีก
Just go back.
ท่านรีบกลับไปเถอะ
Don't delay
อย่าให้เสียเวลา
the military preparations.
ขานชื่อในกองทัพเลย
♪I'm willing to sacrifice for you♪
♪ยอมตัดความปรารถนาเพื่อเจ้า♪
♪If love still remembers the promises we made♪
♪หากความรักจำได้ เราเคยสัญญา♪
♪Even if this love hurts me, I'll continue living for you♪
♪ต่อให้รักนี้ทำร้ายข้า ก็จะมีชีวิตอยู่เพื่อเจ้า♪
♪Holding onto the memories♪
♪ไปตามเค้าโครงในความทรงจำ♪
♪Waiting is my persistence♪
♪รอคอยคนที่ข้ายึดติด♪
♪If love remembers the promise I made to you♪
♪หากความรักจำได้ สัญญาที่รักษาเพื่อเจ้า♪
♪I'm willing to sacrifice for you♪
♪ยอมตัดความปรารถนาเพื่อเจ้า♪
♪As I wait for your answer♪
♪รอเจ้าตอบข้าเสมอ♪
Mister Shiqi,
สือชีหลาง
I knew you would come this way when you left the pass.
ข้าว่าแล้ว
So, I brought our men
เลยพาพวกพี่น้อง
to meet you here.
มาหนุนท่าน
So, what do you think?
เป็นอย่างไร
We're pretty loyal, right?
มีน้ำใจพอไหม
Unlike someone
ไม่เหมือนใครบางคน
who knocked out his brother.
ฟาดพี่น้องตัวเองสลบหมด
Go back first.
กลับไปก่อน
There's an ambush nearby.
มีคนซุ่มโจมตีอยู่ใกล้ ๆ
All right.
ได้เลย
Withdraw.
ถอนกำลัง
Taozi.
เถาจื่อ
I brought
ข้าเอาผลไม้แห้ง
your favorite dried nuts.
ที่เจ้าชอบกินที่สุดมาให้
Here you go.
อ้าว
What's wrong?
เป็นอะไร
Don't you want to eat dried nuts anymore?
แม้แต่ผลไม้แห้งเจ้าก็ไม่อยากกินหรือ
It's not that I don't want to eat dried nuts.
ไม่ใช่ไม่อยากกินผลไม้แห้ง
It's just that tomorrow
แต่พรุ่งนี้
I have to leave with Lieutenant He
ข้ากับนายกอง
after the troops withdraw.
จะถอนทัพไปพร้อมกองทัพแล้ว
Why so soon?
ทำไม ทำไมเร็วแบบนี้
The Great General learned
แม่ทัพใหญ่รู้ว่า
that the Lieutenant He suddenly fell seriously ill.
นายกองป่วยหนักกะทันหัน
He was extremely worried
เขาเป็นห่วงมาก
But he's the Great General
แต่เขาเป็นแม่ทัพใหญ่
in charge of two towns.
ที่ปกครองสองเมือง
If he appears abruptly at Tong Pass,
หากผลีผลามปรากฏตัวที่ด่านถง
it might lead to misunderstandings in the court.
กลัวว่าในราชสำนักจะเข้าใจผิด
So, the Lieutenant He said we have to withdraw quickly.
ดังนั้นนายกองบอกว่า
So, we can meet the Great General on the way.
ระหว่างทางจะได้เจอกับแม่ทัพใหญ่
Then, I'll go send you off tomorrow.
อย่างนั้นพรุ่งนี้ข้าไปส่งเจ้า
Don't bother.
เจ้าอย่ามาเลย
Lieutenant He is not in a good mood.
นายกองอารมณ์ไม่ดี
I don't want her
ข้าไม่อยากให้นางเห็น
to see anyone from the Zhenxi Army.
คนของกองทัพเจิ้นซี
I'll go and talk to Mister Shiqi
ข้าจะไปบอกสือชีหลางเดี๋ยวนี้
to apologize to the Lieutenant He.
ให้เขามาขอขมานายกอง
Come back here.
เจ้ากลับมาเลยนะ
Don't interfere
ไม่รู้อะไร
if you don't know anything.
ก็อย่ายุ่งมั่วซั่วสิ
But...
แต่ว่า
But I don't want to part ways with you.
แต่ว่าข้าไม่อยากแยกจากเจ้า
What you see in dreams may not be as real as what you see in paintings.
ในฝันอาจไม่ได้พบคนในดวงใจ
So, parting ways may not be as sad as you think it is.
โลกนี้จากนานจักไม่เศร้า
What does that mean?
หมาย หมายความว่าอะไร
Lieutenant He said it.
นายกองข้าบอกว่า
It means
ความหมายคือ
if people stay apart long enough,
ขอแค่จากกันนานพอ
they won't feel sad anymore.
คนก็จะไม่รู้สึกเศร้า
I see it differently.
ข้าไม่คิดแบบนี้
As long we stay apart,
ตราบใดที่ข้าแยกจากเจ้า
I would feel sad.
ข้าก็จะรู้สึกเศร้า
If we stay apart long enough,
ถ้าแยกจากเจ้านานเข้า
I would be very sad.
อย่างนั้นข้าจะเสียใจมาก
Why are you doing this?
ทำเช่นนี้เพื่ออะไร
Not even giving her a farewell.
แม้แต่ส่งก็ไม่ไปส่ง
Instead, you're standing here,
ทีตอนนี้มายืนอยู่นี่
staring at the empty space.
มองที่โล่ง ๆ แล้วเหม่อลอย
Who says I'm staring at the empty space?
ใครบอกข้ามองที่โล่ง ๆ
I'm looking at the terrain on both sides.
ข้าดูสภาพภูเขาสองข้างต่างหาก
Whether you look or not doesn't matter now.
ตอนนี้ดูหรือเปล่าก็ไม่สำคัญแล้ว
What matters
ที่สำคัญคือ
is when you start feeling empty inside while waiting here.
อีกสักครู่รอท่าน
Only then you'll know what it feels like.
ท่านก็จะรู้รสชาติเอง
Here.
มา
Did the people we sent out last night
คนที่ส่งไปเมื่อคืน
find anything?
สืบได้อะไรไหม
There are some traces in this forest.
ในป่ามีร่องรอยอยู่บ้าง
But it's hard to tell.
แต่ดูอะไรไม่ออก
Those people are very cautious
คนพวกนั้นทำงาน
in their actions.
รอบคอบมาก
Oh!
จริงสิ
Could it be
จะพุ่งเป้าไปที่
that they are targeting Miss Cui?
คุณหนูชุยหรือเปล่า
I heard Miss Cui
ข้าได้ยินว่าคุณหนูชุย
is still not well.
ยังไม่หายป่วยดีเลย
When she left,
ตอนไป
she traveled in a carriage.
ต้องนั่งรถม้าไป
Aren't you going to escort her?
ท่านไม่ไปคุ้มกันหรือ
They're not going after her.
ไม่ใช่นาง
They're likely after me.
แปดในสิบส่วนเป้าหมายคือข้า
Besides,
อีกอย่าง
she has the army guarding her,
นางมีกองทัพล้อมอารักขา
and her father
พ่อของนาง
also sent elite soldiers to meet up with her.
ก็ส่งทหารฝีมือดีมาหนุนอีก
She'll be fine.
นางไม่เป็นไรหรอก
You sure
ข้าว่าท่านนะ
are stubborn.
ก็คือปากแข็ง
If you don't go after her,
ท่านไม่ไล่ตามไป
you'll regret it in the future.
ต่อไปต้องเสียใจทีหลังแน่
We should focus
คิดเรื่อง
on important matters.
จริงจังดีกว่า
We've secured Tong Pass,
ด่านถงมั่นคงแล้ว
and the army should return to the capital.
กองทัพก็ควรกลับเมืองหลวงแล้ว
What are you looking at?
ดูอะไรอยู่
I'm watching
ข้ากำลังดูบนฟ้า
two lonely geese in the sky.
มีห่านป่าสองตัว
One is heading south, and the other is heading north.
ตัวหนึ่งไปทางใต้ ตัวหนึ่งไปทางเหนือ
It's quite pitiful.
ช่างน่าสงสาร
I wonder
ไม่รู้ว่าพวกมัน
if they can fly together.
จะได้บินด้วยกันอีกไหม
Lord Qin requested to return to the capital
อ๋องฉินทูลขอกลับราชสำนัก
and will be back today.
วันนี้กลับเมืองหลวงแล้ว
whether to have the officials welcome him.
จะให้เหล่าขุนนางไปต้อนรับไหม
But Lord Qin declined.
อ๋องฉินพอรู้เข้าก็ปฏิเสธไป
However, today,
แต่วันนี้
all the young ladies in the city
สตรีทั่วเมืองหลวง
rushed to the streets
ออกไปอยู่ที่ถนนกันหมด
to see Lord Qin leading the army
ไปดูอ๋องฉินนำทัพ
returning with victory.
ได้ชัยชนะกลับมา
It's widely spread
ต่างลือกันว่า
that Lord Qin is truly valiant
อ๋องฉินช่างกล้าหาญไร้ผู้เทียมทาน
and awe-inspiring.
องอาจสง่างาม
Father, say whatever you want to say.
ท่านพ่ออยากพูดอะไรก็พูดเถอะเจ้าค่ะ
When do you plan
เจ้ากะจะ
to visit Lord Qin?
ไปพบอ๋องฉินเมื่อไร
Three days later.
สามวันให้หลัง
Why three days later?
เหตุใดเป็นสามวันให้หลัง
I'm waiting for someone.
หว่านเหนียงรอคนผู้หนึ่งอยู่
When that person arrives,
รอคนผู้นั้นถึงแล้ว
only then I can go
หว่านเหนียงถึง
and meet Lord Qin.
ไปพบอ๋องฉินได้
Hey, Bao.
พี่เป้า
Shiqi,
สือชีหลาง
since we have nothing to do today,
วันนี้ว่างไม่มีอะไรทำ
let's go out of the city for a horse ride.
เราไปควบม้านอกเมืองกัน
No.
ไม่ไป
I heard Fengying Pavilion has received a batch of good alcohol.
ได้ยินว่า
Let's go for a drink.
เราไปดื่มสุรากัน
No.
ไม่ไป
What's going on with you?
นี่มันเกิดอะไรขึ้น
Ever since we returned to the capital,
ตั้งแต่ระหว่างทางที่กลับเมืองหลวง
you've changed like a different person.
ก็เหมือนเปลี่ยนไปเป็นคนละคน
You're moody all day
ดูซึม ๆ ทั้งวัน
and even pulling a long face.
แถมยังทำหน้าบูดหน้าบึ้งอีก
What happened?
ทำไม
Who made you angry?
ใครทำให้ท่านโกรธหรือ
Or
หรือว่า
did someone offend you
ใครรังแก
and you're upset about it?
อ๋องฉินของเรา
In this world,
ในโลกนี้นะ
one thing can conquer another.
(มหาสมุทรเป็นที่รวมของสรรพสิ่ง) ของสิ่งหนึ่งย่อมพิชิตอีกสิ่งหนึ่ง
Do you think no one can deal
เจ้าคิดว่าอ๋องฉินที่ห้าวหาญไร้เทียมทาน
with the mighty and invincible Lord Qin?
จะไม่มีคนทำอะไรเขาได้อย่างนั้นหรือ
Stop talking in riddles
เจ้าอย่ามาใบ้คำกับข้า
and just tell me.
พูดสิ
Don't listen to his nonsense.
อย่าฟังเขาพูดเหลวไหล
Me? Talking nonsense?
ข้าเนี่ยนะพูดเหลวไหล
It's better than someone being bothered
อย่างไรก็ดีกว่าใครบางคนจิตใจว้าวุ่น
with wild thoughts.
คิดเหลวไหลกระมัง
Mister Shiqi, Miss Gu is seeking an audience.
สือชีหลาง คุณหนูกู้ขอพบ
Greetings, Lord Qin.
อ๋องฉิน
Your Highness.
ท่านอ๋อง
Miss Gu, you're too kind.
คุณหนูกู้เกรงใจแล้ว
Nanny?
แม่นม
Nanny, please sit.
แม่นม นั่ง
Shiqi,
สือชีหลาง
you're all grown-up now.
ท่านโตแล้ว
Our little young master
คุณชายน้อย
is now Lord Qin.
กลายเป็นอ๋องฉินแล้ว
Since I arrived in the capital,
พอข้ามาถึงเมืองหลวง
I've heard everyone praising
ก็ได้ยินคนในเมืองใคร ๆ ก็ชม
Lord Qin for his might.
ว่าอ๋องฉินน่าเกรงขาม
Every young lady wants
แม่นางแต่ละคน
to marry Lord Qin.
ล้วนอยากแต่งงานกับอ๋องฉิน
Nanny, why are you here?
แม่นม ท่านมาได้อย่างไร
I've been living in the countryside for many years.
ข้าอยู่บ้านนอก
I'm not feeling well
สุขภาพไม่ดี
and no one could send me to the capital.
แล้วก็ไม่มีคนส่งข้าเข้าเมือง
This time,
ครั้งนี้
it's all thanks to Miss Gu
ดีที่ได้คุณหนูกู้
who somehow managed to send someone to find me,
ไม่รู้อย่างไร
asking if I wanted to see you.
ถามข้าว่าอยากมาเยี่ยมท่านไหม
Of course, I'm happy to do so.
ข้าต้องเต็มใจอยู่แล้ว
Now that I've seen you,
ครั้งนี้ได้เห็นสือชีหลาง
I can die happily
ต่อให้ข้าตายทันที
even if I die now.
ข้าก็ยอม
Nanny,
แม่นม
don't say such things.
อย่าพูดเช่นนี้
I'm happy.
ข้าดีใจ
Nanny,
แม่นม
since you're here,
ในเมื่อมาแล้ว
stay with us.
ก็อยู่ที่นี่เถอะ
My residence is quite spacious.
จวนอ๋องฉินใหญ่มาก
You can stay wherever you like.
ท่านอยากอยู่ไหนก็อยู่
All right.
ได้
You've grown up. You're all grown up.
โตแล้ว ๆ
Your Highness,
ท่านอ๋อง
she's used to taking an afternoon nap.
คนแก่คนเฒ่านอนกลางวันชินแล้ว
I've just
ข้าเพิ่งปรนนิบัติ
assisted her to sleep.
นางหลับไป
You can rest assured, Your Highness.
ท่านอ๋องวางใจได้
Thank you, Miss Gu.
ขอบคุณคุณหนูกู้
It's a small matter, not worth mentioning.
เรื่องเล็กพวกนี้ ไม่มีค่าควรแก่การพูดถึง
Nanny is getting old.
แม่นมอายุมากแล้ว
I once sent people to find her.
ข้าก็เคยส่งคนไปตามหานาง
But it was in vain.
แต่มักไม่ได้ผลกลับมา
I even thought
ข้ากระทั่งคิดว่า
I would never see her again.
จะไม่ได้พบนางอีกแล้ว
The nanny's own son
บุตรชายแท้ ๆ ของแม่นม
is very unfilial.
อกตัญญูมาก
I didn't give him money.
ข้าไม่ได้ให้เงินทองเขา
Instead, I asked village head to question him thoroughly.
แต่ให้ผู้ใหญ่บ้านตำหนิเขาอย่างหนัก
Nanny's family is poor.
แม่นมที่บ้านยากจน
So, I bought a few acres of good land
ดังนั้นข้าใช้นามของท่านอ๋อง
in your name.
ซื้อที่นาสองสามแปลง
The deed
ในโฉนด
is all in the nanny's name.
เขียนชื่อแม่นมทั้งหมด
In the future,
เช่นนี้
if she doesn't want to stay in your residence
ต่อไปหากนาง
and wants to retire to the countryside,
กลับไปใช้ชีวิตบ้านปลายในชนบท
it should be enough.
ก็เพียงพอ
Miss Gu,
คุณหนูกู้
you're a kind and thoughtful person.
เจ้าเป็นคนจิตใจดีละเอียดอ่อนจริง ๆ
Thank you.
ขอบคุณมาก
Also, the money used to buy the land
จริงสิ เงินที่ซื้อที่นา
will be sent
อีกสักครู่
to your residence later.
ข้าจะสั่งคนส่งไปที่จวน
Your Highness, you're too kind.
ท่านอ๋องเกรงใจแล้ว
I'm not smart since I was a child.
ข้าโง่เขลามาตั้งแต่เด็ก
To be honest,
บอกตรง ๆ
I'm not favored by my parents.
อยู่ที่บ้านก็ไม่เป็นที่รักของพ่อแม่
So, whenever someone is a little kind to me,
ดังนั้นขอเพียงมีคน
I'm very grateful.
ข้าก็จะซึ้งใจมาก
Your Highness, you saved my life.
ท่านอ๋องมีบุญคุณช่วยชีวิตข้า
I can never repay
บุญคุณใหญ่หลวงเช่นนี้
such great kindness.
หว่านเหนียงไม่มีสิ่งใดตอบแทน
So, I can only do some
ได้แต่ทำเรื่องเล็ก ๆ น้อย ๆ
little things within my ability.
ที่พอทำได้
I only hope you will always be happy.
ขอเพียงท่านอ๋องมีความสุขบ่อย ๆ
That's enough for me to be very happy.
เช่นนี้หว่านเหนียงก็ดีใจแล้ว
Thank you.
ขอบคุณ
The officials advised me
เหล่าขุนนางต่างเตือนเราว่า
to reward Cui Yi
ต้องปูนบำเหน็จให้ชุยอี่ด้วย
and to ingratiate myself
ยังจะให้เราผูกมัดใจเขาด้วย
with the Cui family.
พวกเขาสกุลชุย
He already controls two prefectures,
ปกครองผิงเหลียง
Pingliang and Weiyang.
เว่ยหยางสองเมืองแล้ว
How can I reward them?
จะให้เราปูนบำเหน็จอย่างไรอีก
Besides,
อีกอย่าง
he doesn't have a son whom I can confer a title to.
เขาก็ไม่มีลูกชายสืบทอดตำแหน่งได้
What can I do to properly win the Cui family over?
ตกลงมีวิธีอะไร
Father,
เสด็จพ่อ
I have an idea.
ในใจลูกมีความคิดอยู่
Tell me quickly.
พูดเร็ว
I heard
ได้ยินว่าชุยอี่
Cui Yi has a daughter,
มีบุตรีแค่คนเดียว
and she grew up in the military,
ยิ่งกว่านั้นยังโตมาในกองทัพ
not inferior to a son.
ไม่ด้อยกว่าบุรุษ
Since I have not yet married,
ลูกจนถึงตอนนี้ยังไม่แต่งงาน
how about Father bestows Miss Cui
ไม่สู้เสด็จพ่อพระราชทานสมรส
in marriage to me?
ให้ลูกกับบุตรีสกุลชุย
This way,
เช่นนี้แล้ว
Miss Cui
บุตรีสกุลชุย
becomes your daughter-in-law,
ก็จะกลายเป็นลูกสะใภ้ของเสด็จพ่อ
and Cui Yi
ส่วนชุยอี่
becomes my father-in-law.
ก็จะกลายเป็นพ่อตาของลูก
Even if, in the future,
ต่อให้อนาคต
I ask him to withdraw from Dongdu, it may be possible too.
ให้เขาถอยออกจากเมืองตง
Good.
ดี
This plan is good, very good.
วิธีนี้ดี ดีมาก
I just don't know
เพียงแต่ไม่รู้ว่าบุตรีสกุลชุยคนนี้
what Miss Cui looks like.
หน้าตาเป็นอย่างไร
If she grew up in the military,
เจ้าบอกว่านางโตในกองทัพตั้งแต่เด็ก
is she rough?
จะใช่คนหยาบคายหรือไม่
If her appearance is ugly
หากรูปโฉมทั้งอัปลักษณ์
and her temperament is coarse,
นิสัยก็หยาบโลนอีกละก็
wouldn't it
มิเป็นการ
be really unfair to you?
ไม่เป็นธรรมต่อเจ้าอย่างมากหรือ
I am your son.
ลูกเป็นโอรสของเสด็จพ่อ
So, I should share your worries.
ควรช่วยเสด็จพ่อแบ่งเบา
Winning the Cui family is to avoid suspicion
ดึงสกุลชุยมาเป็นพวก
between the ruler and the subject.
หลีกเลี่ยงกษัตริย์ขุนนางแคลงใจกัน
This is my duty.
นี่คือหน้าที่ที่ลูกควรทำ
Father, rest assured.
เสด็จพ่อวางพระทัย
Regardless of what Miss Cui's appearance and character are like,
ไม่ว่าบุตรีสกุลชุย
I am willing to marry her
ลูกก็ยินดีแต่งงานกับนาง
and treat her well,
และดีต่อนาง
ensuring the Cui family
จากนี้ให้สกุลชุย
remains loyal to you.
จงรักภักดีต่อเสด็จพ่อ
Lai,
ไหลเอ๋อร์
you are the one who considers the overall situation.
เจ้าเห็นแก่ส่วนรวมที่สุด
But don't worry.
แต่เจ้าวางใจ
In the future,
ต่อไปเสด็จพ่อ
I'll definitely give you several beautiful women
จะประทานสาวงามสองสามคน
to serve you as side consorts.
ให้เจ้าเป็นชายารองแน่นอน
I won't let you suffer
ไม่ให้เจ้าต้องได้รับ
such unfairness for nothing.
ความไม่เป็นธรรมเปล่า ๆ เช่นนี้
Don't worry.
วางใจเถอะ
Father, have some tea.
เสด็จพ่อเสวยพระสุธารสชา
All right.
ดี
Are you saying
ท่านบอกว่า
someone from the court sent a message saying
ในราชสำนักส่งคนมา
they want me to marry Lord Qi?
บอกว่าอยากให้ข้าแต่งงานกับอ๋องฉี
He's aiming at someone outside of his league.
คางคกริกินเนื้อห่านฟ้า
Who does Lord Qi think he is?
อ๋องฉีเป็นใคร
I can't believe he asks for your hand in marriage.
ก็คิดจะแต่งงานกับลูกสาวข้า
The Emperor is indeed Li Ni's father.
ฮ่องเต้เป็นพ่อหลี่นี่จริง ๆ
Like father, like son,
พ่อลูกสองคนนี้เหมือนกัน
who don't know their place.
ไม่รู้ฟ้าสูงแผ่นดินต่ำ
All right, I'll stop.
เอาละ ไม่พูดถึง
I'll stop talking about the person who was not to know good from bad.
ไม่พูดถึงไอ้สารเลว
Father,
ท่านพ่อ
I'm thinking,
ข้ากำลังคิดว่า
since someone from the court has such intentions,
ในเมื่อในราชสำนักมีคน
why don't we play along
อย่างนั้นเราไม่สู้แผนซ้อนแผน
and turn the tables on them?
ตลบหลังรุกฆาตพวกเขา
Ying,
อาอิ๋ง
do you mean...
เจ้าหมายความว่า
We will openly write a memorial
เราถวายฎีกาต่อฮ่องเต้
to the Emperor.
อย่างสง่าผ่าเผย
In the memorial,
บอกไปว่า
I agree to marry a prince.
อยากให้ข้าแต่งงานกับองค์ชาย ได้
But I want to choose
แต่ต้องทำตามความปรารถนาของข้า
my husband
ต้องให้ข้าเลือกผู้ที่จะแต่งงานด้วย ด้วยตัวเอง
among the princes.
จากในบรรดาองค์ชาย
That Li Ni doesn't know his place.
หลี่นี่นั่นไม่รู้ดีชั่ว
Do you still want to marry him?
หรือว่าเจ้ายังอยากแต่งงานกับเขา
Whether or not I marry him is another matter.
ข้าแต่งหรือไม่แต่งกับเขา เป็นอีกเรื่องหนึ่ง
But since someone in the court
แต่ในเมื่อในราชสำนักมีคน
already has designs on our Cui family,
จ้องจะจัดการกับสกุลชุยเราแล้ว
why not be straightforward
อย่างนั้นเราไม่สู้ใช้แผนในที่แจ้ง
and use their own tricks against them?
อย่างสง่าผ่าเผย
Are you saying...
เจ้าหมายถึง
As long as I say
ขอเพียงข้าบอกว่า
I want to choose a husband from among the princes,
จะเลือกคนแต่งงานด้วยจากในบรรดาองค์ชาย
there will be a big commotion.
ก็จะมี
I don't know what actions
พี่ชายสองคนนี้ของหลี่นี่
Li Ni's two older brothers
ยังไม่รู้
might take.
จะทำเรื่องอะไรออกมาได้
I'm curious to see
ข้าจะขอดูหน่อย
how shameless
ว่าพวกเขาจะไร้ยางอาย
they can be.
ถึงขั้นไหน
I'm also curious
และข้าก็จะดูว่า
about Li Ni's reaction.
หลี่นี่จะมีปฏิกิริยาอย่างไร
Ying,
อาอิ๋ง
this is your lifelong matter.
นี่เป็นเรื่องสำคัญของชีวิตเจ้า
Don't act in anger.
จะเอาแต่อารมณ์ไม่ได้นะ
Father, I'm not doing this out of anger.
ท่านพ่อ ข้าไม่ได้เอาแต่อารมณ์
Now,
บัดนี้
you have control over Pingliang and Weiyang,
ท่านปกครองผิงเหลียง เว่ยหยาง
and our Cui Army is strong.
กองทัพสกุลชุยเราก็กำลังทหารแข็งแกร่ง
Many in the court are uneasy,
ในราชสำนักมีคนนั่งไม่ติดนานแล้ว
seeing us as a piece of meat
เห็นเราเป็นชิ้นเนื้อมัน
everyone wants to grab.
ใคร ๆ ก็อยากเข้ามาแย่งกัดสักคำ
In that case,
เมื่อเป็นเช่นนี้
why not make the first move
ไม่สู้เราทำลายแผนพวกเขาก่อน
and weaken them
ให้พวกเขา
with internal conflicts first?
ตีกันเองให้หัวร้างข้างแตกก่อน
You must think carefully.
เจ้าต้องคิดดี ๆ นะ
Once I submit this memorial,
เมื่อไรที่ถวายฎีกาขึ้นไป
you can only choose your future husband
สามีในอนาคตของเจ้า
from among the three princes.
ก็ได้แต่เลือกจากในองค์ชายสามคนแล้ว
There's no turning back after that.
ง้างธนูแล้วหันกลับไม่ได้
The final outcome
สุดท้ายผลเป็นอย่างไร
may not go as we wish.
อาจไม่เป็นไปตามที่เราต้องการจริง ๆ
Father,
ท่านพ่อ
I've considered
ส่วนได้ส่วนเสียในเรื่องนี้
the interests and risks involved.
ลูกคิดดีแล้ว
Life is like a chess game.
เรื่องในโลกเหมือนกระดานหมากรุก
This world
ใต้หล้านี้
is the biggest game.
ก็คือกระดานหมากที่ใหญ่ที่สุด
I want to be the one playing the chess.
ลูกอยากเป็นคนเดินหมาก
Lord Qin has too many concerns in his heart
อ๋องฉินในใจมีห่วงมากเกินไป
and has no interest in being the crown prince.
ไม่สนใจตำแหน่งรัชทายาท
I had a long talk with him.
ลูกเคยคุยกับเขาอย่างใกล้ชิด
But it had little effect.
แต่ได้ผลน้อยมาก
Since he's willing to be a chess piece,
ในเมื่อเขายอมเป็นหมาก
even if I have to force him,
อย่างนั้นต่อให้ลูกต้องบีบบังคับ
I will make him
ก็จะบีบบังคับให้เขา
the other player.
เป็นคนเดินหมากอีกคน
Father,
ท่านพ่อ
I want to take this risk.
ข้าอยากเดิมพันครั้งนี้
Your Majesty,
ฝ่าบาท
in Cui Yi's memorial,
ในฎีกาชุยอี่บอกว่า
it claims Your Majesty intends
ฝ่าบาททรงแสดงเจตจำนง
to bestow his daughter's marriage to Lord Qi.
อยากยกบุตรีของเขาให้อภิเษกสมรสกับอ๋องฉี
Is this true?
เรื่องนี้จริงหรือไม่พ่ะย่ะค่ะ
I did send someone to inquire.
เราส่งคน
Your Majesty's intention is the imperial decree.
พระประสงค์ของฝ่าบาทก็คือราชโองการ
However, as a subject,
แต่เขาที่เป็นขุนนาง
he dared to speak arrogantly,
กลับพูดจาสามหาว
wanting to choose a son-in-law among the princes for his daughter
จะเลือกลูกเขยให้บุตรีจากในบรรดาองค์ชาย
as if court customs meant nothing.
ไม่เห็นมารยาทและกฎของราชสำนักในสายตา
I ask Your Majesty to issue a decree
ขอให้ฝ่าบาททรงมีราชโองการตำหนิ
to rectify the court's morals.
เพื่อจัดระเบียบราชสำนัก
That's right!
ถูกต้อง
Cui Yi
ชุยอี่คนนี้
is indeed too arrogant.
ไม่เห็นคนอื่นในสายตาจริง ๆ
Does he see the imperial family as a marketplace
เขานึกว่าราชวงศ์เป็นตลาดสดหรือ
where he can pick and choose?
อยากเลือกก็เลือก
Your Majesty,
ฝ่าบาท
Cui Yi controls two prefectures,
ชุยอี่ปกครอง
Pingliang and Weiyang,
ผิงเหลียง เว่ยหยางสองเมือง
and now occupies Dongdu.
อีกทั้งยึดครองเมืองตง
The court is already worried
ทั่วทั้งราชสำนัก
about his excessive power
เดิมทีก็กังวลว่าเขามีอำนาจมากเกินไป
without any checks.
ไร้ผู้ควบคุม
It is wise for Your Majesty
ฝ่าบาทปราดเปรื่อง
to choose Miss Cui as daughter-in-law.
ยอมเลือกบุตรีสกุลชุยเป็นพระชายาองค์ชาย
Now,
บัดนี้
it's only a gentle appeal from Cui Yi requesting
ชุยอี่เพียงแค่ขออ้อม ๆ
to choose an imperial prince for his daughter.
เลือกองค์ชายมาเป็นเขยเพื่อบุตรี
Your Majesty, why not agree?
ฝ่าบาทไม่สู้ทรงอนุญาต
This action costs no soldiers or resources
ทำเช่นนี้ไม่ต้องเสียทหารแม้นายเดียว
and can bring the military power of the Cui family under control.
ก็ริบอำนาจทหารสกุลชุยกลับมาได้
It's truly clever.
ช่างแยบยลจริง ๆ
I also think this idea is not bad.
เรา
However, for my son
แต่โอรสของเรา
to marry his daughter
จะแต่งงานกับบุตรีของเขา
is the ultimate honor
นั่นคือเกียรติอย่างสูงสุด
for the Cui family.
ของสกุลชุย
How can they send a memorial
จะถวายฎีกา
suggesting to choose one themselves?
บอกว่าจะเลือกเองคนหนึ่งได้อย่างไร
Your Majesty's words are correct.
ฝ่าบาทตรัสได้ถูกต้อง
The Cui family is impudent!
สกุลชุยไร้มารยาท
How can Miss Cui be worthy of becoming a princess consort?
บุตรีสกุลชุยจะเป็นชายาองค์ชายได้อย่างไร
However, as a ruler,
ฝ่าบาทเป็นฮ่องเต้
His Majesty has a broad mind and can tolerate the world.
พระทัยกว้างขวาง สามารถรองรับใต้หล้า
What the Cui family has done, His Majesty can surely forgive.
การกระทำของสกุลชุย
Putting the ruler before the subjects is just and proper!
ฮ่องเต้ก่อนถึงจะเป็นขุนนาง สมเหตุสมผล
There is no reason for a subject
มีอย่างที่ไหน
to choose an imperial son-in-law.
ขุนนางเลือกองค์ชายเป็นเขย
You are stuck in outdated ways,
ท่านมันหัวโบราณ
resistant to change!
ไม่รู้จักเปลี่ยนแปลงตามสมควร
You're old-fashioned and rigid!
อย่างท่านเรียกว่าคร่ำครึ
By speaking like this,
ท่านพูดเช่นนี้
you're not showing respect to His Majesty
ผิดต่อฝ่าบาทหรือไม่
or honoring the traditions of our ancestors!
ผิดต่อบรรพบุรุษหรือไม่
You truly lack an understanding of etiquette!
อย่างท่านเรียกว่าไม่รู้มารยาท
You forgot the teaching of the ancestors!
ท่านลืมบรรพบุรุษ
(Lord Xin's Residence)
(จวนอ๋องซิ่น)
Thank you, sister-in-law.
ขอบคุณพี่สะใภ้
You're too kind, Lai.
น้องรองเกรงใจไปแล้ว
I'll leave you two to talk.
พวกท่านพี่น้องค่อย ๆ คุย
Jun, you sure have married the right woman.
พี่ใหญ่ได้แต่งงาน
I'm truly envious.
น้องอิจฉาเหลือเกิน
You rushed to my residence right after the morning court ended.
พอเลิกประชุม
What do you want?
ตกลงมีเรื่องอะไรกันแน่
Jun,
พี่ใหญ่
you must help me this time.
ครั้งนี้ท่านต้องช่วยข้านะ
Cui Yi said he wants to choose a son-in-law between me and Li Ni.
ชุยอี่บอกว่า
selecting among the princes.
จะเลือกเขยจากบรรดาองค์ชายต่างหาก
I was thinking
ข้าคิดว่าพี่ใหญ่
that you already have a princess consort.
แต่งงานมีชายาแล้ว
I supposed Miss Cui wouldn't want
คิดว่าคุณหนูชุยนั่น
to be a side consort.
คงไม่ยอมแต่งมาเป็นชายารอง
So, I thought
ดังนั้นข้าถึงคิดว่า
if you could help me
หากพี่ใหญ่ช่วยข้าได้
get the support of the Cui family,
หากข้าได้
I could definitely assist you in moving into the Eastern Palace.
ต่อไปจะต้อง
What do you think, Jun?
พี่ใหญ่คิดอย่างไร
You have a point.
น้องรองพูดมีเหตุผล
We must not
คุณหนูชุยคนนี้
let Miss Cui marry Li Ni.
แต่งงานกับหลี่นี่ไม่ได้เด็ดขาด
Thank you, Jun.
อย่างนั้นก็ขอบคุณพี่ใหญ่แล้ว
I'm impressed with Miss Cui
คุณหนูชุยคนนี้ ข้ายอม
with all my heart and sincerely convinced.
อย่างหมอบราบคาบ ยอมด้วยใจจริง
You see,
พวกเจ้าลองว่ามา
His Majesty wants to marry Miss Cui to Lord Qi.
ฝ่าบาทจะให้คุณหนูชุย
See how clever she was?
นางฉลาดแค่ไหน
She voluntarily submitted a memorial,
เป็นฝ่ายถวายฎีกาเองเลย
stating that she wanted
บอกว่าตัวเอง
to choose a husband from the princes.
จะเลือกคนหนึ่งจากในบรรดาองค์ชาย
Isn't it obvious
แบบนี้ยังไม่ชัดอีกหรือ
that she wants to marry Mister Shiqi?
นางจะแต่งกับสือชีหลางอย่างไรล่ะ
- Exactly! - That's right!
นั่นสิ ๆ
Mister Shiqi,
สือชีหลาง
you have to show her some gestures.
อย่างไรท่านก็ต้องแสดงออกให้นางรู้หน่อยสิ
Yes, show some gestures.
ต้องแสดงออกให้รู้
- Yes, you need to. - Do it.
ต้อง ๆ ๆ
She only said
นางแค่บอกว่า
to pick among the princes.
จะเลือกคนหนึ่งจากในบรรดาองค์ชาย
She didn't say it was me.
ไม่ได้บอกว่าเป็นข้าซะหน่อย
Stop being stubborn.
ท่านอย่าปากแข็งเลย
As a young lady,
นางเป็นผู้หญิง
do you expect her to name you directly
หรือว่าต้องให้ระบุชื่อ
to marry you?
ว่าจะแต่งกับท่าน
Who else would she marry
นางไม่อยากแต่งกับท่าน
if not you?
แล้วจะแต่งกับใครล่ะ
That's right.
ใช่
If she doesn't want to marry you,
นางไม่อยากแต่งกับท่าน
why would she submit
แล้วนางจะ
such a memorial to His Majesty?
ถวายฎีกานี้ทำไม
- That's right! - Precisely.
ใช่ไหม
- Shiqi. - Exactly.
ใช่
Marrying Miss Cui would be having the best of both worlds,
นั่นสิ ๆ
am I right?
ถูกไหม
Miss Cui
แม้คุณหนูชุยคนนี้
may be formidable at times.
ปกตินิสัยนาง
But she's Cui Yi's only daughter.
แต่ว่านะ
In the future, her husband
ต่อไปทั้งกองทัพสกุลชุย
will oversee the entire Cui Army.
ก็ต้องให้เขยของนางมาคุม
So, can we
แล้วพวกเราว่า
let Lord Qi gain
เรื่องดี ๆ แบบนี้
this favorable situation?
จะ จะยกให้อ๋องฉีได้หรือ
Of course not!
ไม่ได้สิ
Right.
ถูกต้อง
- No way! - We can't let him have it.
ไม่ได้ จะยกให้ได้อย่างไร
But that's not the crucial part.
แต่ว่า พี่น้อง นี่ไม่สำคัญ
What matters most?
ที่สำคัญที่สุดคืออะไร
It's that Miss Cui
ก็คือคุณหนูชุย
already has good feelings toward Shiqi.
เดิมก็มีไมตรี
General Pei Yuan
ข้าคิดว่าแม่ทัพน้อยเผย
is absolutely right.
พูดถูกมาก
Ear,
เอ่อร์ตัว
you must be happy this time, right?
คราวนี้เจ้าดีใจแย่เลยสินะ
If Miss Cui marries Mister Shiqi,
คุณหนูชุยแต่งงานกับสือชีหลางของเรา
Taozi will naturally come
แม่นางเถาจื่อก็ย่อม
to Lord Qin's Residence.
มาอยู่จวนอ๋องของเรา
Then, you two
ถึงเวลาพวกเจ้าสองคนก็ได้
can live together happily.
บินเคียงคู่กันไม่ใช่หรือ
Yes, live a blissful life together.
บินเคียงคู่
Mister Shiqi.
สือชีหลาง
Yes.
นั่นสิ
Miss Cui's dowry
สินเดิมของคุณหนูชุย
must be at least three hundred carts, right?
อย่างน้อยต้องมี 300 หาบกระมัง
It has to be, it has to be.
ต้องมี ๆ
Then our betrothal gifts can't be lacking either.
อย่างนั้นสินสอดของเรา
Indeed.
ใช่
It's our village tradition
กฎในหมู่บ้านเรา
to have a pair of wild geese as part of the betrothal gifts.
ในสินสอดต้องมีห่านป่าคู่หนึ่ง
The groom must personally shoot them.
ที่เจ้าบ่าวยิงเองกับมือ
Since we have nice weather now,
ไม่ก็ฉวยโอกาสที่วันนี้อากาศดี
how about we accompany you outside the city to hunt wild geese?
พวกเราพี่น้อง
That's right.
ใช่
If Mister Shiqi fails to get any,
แล้วถ้าสือชีหลาง
and we manage to shoot the geese,
ยิงเองไม่ถูก
does it count?
แบบนั้นนับไหม
Of course, it doesn't count.
ต้องไม่นับอยู่แล้ว
Didn't he say earlier the groom must personally shoot them?
ก็บอกแล้วไม่ใช่หรือ
Of course, it counts.
ต้องนับอยู่แล้ว
We are Mister Shiqi's brothers,
เราเป็นพี่น้องของสือชีหลาง
his family.
เป็นคนในครอบครัว
Yes.
ใช่
If family shoots, why wouldn't it count?
คนในครอบครัวทำไมจะไม่นับ
- No, it doesn't count. - Yes, it counts.
- ต้องนับ - นับไม่ได้
- No, it can't! - I said it does count.
นับไม่ได้
- It just doesn't count. - All right. Enough already.
นับไม่ได้ก็แล้วกัน
Stop fighting!
อย่าทะเลาะกัน ๆ
Shiqi.
สือชีหลาง
I say it counts.
ข้าบอกว่านับกับเจ้า
Mister Shiqi, where are you going?
เจ้าบ่าว อย่าไปสิ
When are we going to hunt wild geese?
จะไปยิงห่านป่าเมื่อไร
We'll prepare the bows and arrows.
พวกเราพี่น้องจะได้เตรียมธนู
Young Master.
คุณชาย
What do you think
เจ้าว่า
Ying meant
อาอิ๋งถวายฎีกาเล่มนี้
when she submitted this memorial?
หมายความว่าอย่างไร
It's probably
น่าจะเพราะ
because she doesn't want to marry Lord Qi.
นางไม่อยากแต่งกับอ๋องฉี
So, she politely declined.
ถึงได้ปฏิเสธอย่างอ้อม ๆ
It was because she only wanted to marry Li Ni!
เพราะนางอยากแต่งกับหลี่นี่เท่านั้น
Why is Ying doing this to me?
ทำไมอาอิ๋งถึงทำกับข้าเช่นนี้
I have been devoted to her.
ข้ารักมั่นต่อนาง
Can't she see that at all?
นางมองไม่เห็นสักนิดเลยหรือ
Young Master,
คุณชาย
She must have hated me
ที่จริงนายกอง
because I borrowed troops
ข้ายืมทหารของเจียซั่ว
from Jieshuo.
นางถึงได้เกลียดข้า
She can hate if she wants.
เกลียดก็เกลียดเถอะ
As long as I'm with her,
เอาเป็นว่าขอแค่ข้ากับนางอยู่ด้วยกัน
I can slowly persuade her.
ข้าค่อย ๆ กล่อมนาง
Sooner or later, she'll change her mind.
ช้าเร็วนางต้องเปลี่ยนใจ
The place where Ying and I are going
ที่ที่ข้าจะไปกับอาอิ๋ง
is beautiful.
ทิวทัศน์งดงาม
She'll surely like it.
อาอิ๋งต้องชอบแน่
Both of us will stay there
ข้ากับนางจะอยู่ที่นั่น
and live a carefree and leisurely life.
ใช้ชีวิตอย่างอิสระ
Have you prepared
ของว่างที่อาอิ๋งชอบกิน
the snacks she likes?
เจ้าเตรียมไว้หรือยัง
Once Ying and I are there,
ขอแค่ข้ากับอาอิ๋งไปถึงที่นั่น
no one will get in our way anymore.
ก็ไม่มีคน
Mister Shiqi.
สือชีหลาง
Mister Shiqi, we have good news.
สือชีหลาง มีข่าวดี
Miss Cui has sent someone
คุณหนูชุยส่งคนมา
to invite you to a meeting outside the city.
นัดท่านไปเจอกันนอกเมือง
What did I tell you?
ข้าว่าแล้ว
Miss Cui must be looking for you
คุณหนูชุยต้องมาหาท่าน
to discuss this betrothal.
ปรึกษาเรื่องหมั้นหมายแน่
You two like each other.
พวกท่านสองคนใจตรงกัน
This time, Miss Cui
ครั้งนี้คุณหนูชุย
even took the initiative to submit a memorial to His Majesty.
เป็นฝ่ายถวายฎีกาให้ฝ่าบาทอีก
For a young lady
นางเป็นผู้หญิง
to take such a step is not easy.
ทำได้ถึงขั้นนี้
Regardless of any quarrels or disagreements you had in the past,
ไม่ว่าเมื่อก่อนพวกท่าน
now that you'll meet,
ครั้งนี้พบหน้ากัน
make sure to reconcile
ท่านต้องคืนดีกันเหมือนเดิมนะ
and marry her.
รีบแต่งนางเข้าบ้าน
Mister Shiqi, what's wrong?
สือชีหลาง ท่านเป็นอะไร
If she chooses me,
หากนางเลือกข้า
there's no need to meet.
ย่อมไม่ต้องพบ
Since she wants to meet me,
ในเมื่อนัดพบ
I fear there might be some discord.
กลัวแต่เรื่องจะไม่ราบรื่น
Wonderland is still beautiful.
ทุ่งเล่อโหยวยังสวยเหมือนเดิมนะ
Ying,
อาอิ๋ง
back at Tong Pass,
วันนั้นที่ด่านถง
you asked us to think about it individually.
เจ้าให้เราต่างคนต่างไปคิดดู
The Great General submitted a petition,
แม่ทัพใหญ่ถวายฎีกา
and I initially thought
เดิมข้านึกว่า
you were unwilling to marry Lord Qi.
เจ้าไม่เต็มใจแต่งกับอ๋องฉี
That's why you had to submit that memorial.
ถึงถูกบีบให้ถวายฎีกาเล่มนั้น
Life is like a game of chess.
เรื่องในโลกเหมือนกระดานหมากรุก
No one can navigate it alone.
ไม่มีใครสามารถสนใจแต่ตัวเองได้
I'm my father's only daughter.
ท่านพ่อมีข้า
I'm bound to attract the coveting desires of others.
ยากที่จะไม่ให้คนอื่นจ้องตาเป็นมัน
So, are you willing to marry me?
อย่างนั้นเจ้ายินดีแต่งงานกับข้าไหม
My heart is more than willing.
ในใจข้าย่อมยินดีอยู่แล้ว
But what about your two elder brothers?
แต่พี่ชายสองคนนั้นของท่าน
Will they let it happen?
จะยอมให้มันเกิดขึ้นแต่โดยดีหรือ
I told you
ข้าเคยพูดไว้
I'm not interested in crown prince's position.
ข้าไม่สนใจตำแหน่งรัชทายาท
I will find the great imperial grandson
ข้าจะตามหาพระนัดดารัชทายาทกลับมา
and have my father declare him the crown prince,
ให้เสด็จพ่อตั้งพระนัดดารัชทายาท เป็นรัชทายาท
leaving my brothers with no hope.
พวกท่านพี่ก็ไม่มีหวังแล้ว
Do you think your brothers
ท่านคิดว่าพี่ชายสองคนของท่าน
as the crown prince?
ถูกตั้งเป็นรัชทายาทไหม
After the great imperial grandson moves into the Eastern Palace,
ถ้าพระนัดดารัชทายาท เข้าเป็นเจ้าตำหนักบูรพา
can he survive for even a year or so?
เขาจะอยู่รอดถึงปีไหม
With me around,
มีข้าอยู่
I will ensure his safety
ข้าจะต้องปกป้องพระนัดดารัชทายาท
in the Eastern Palace.
ให้ปลอดภัยในตำหนักบูรพา
Even if you can protect
ต่อให้ท่านปกป้อง
the great imperial grandson in court,
พระนัดดารัชทายาทได้ทุกที่ในราชสำนัก
can you guarantee absolute security?
แต่ท่านรับประกันได้ว่า
You're Lord Qin
ท่านคืออ๋องฉิน
with military power in your hands.
อีกทั้งกุมอำนาจทหาร
When your brothers frame you
ถึงเวลาพี่ชายสองคนนั้นของท่าน
and the great imperial grandson for usurping the throne,
ใส่ร้ายว่าท่านกับพระนัดดารัชทายาท สมรู้ร่วมคิดเพื่อชิงบัลลังก์
how are you going to explain that?
ท่านจะแก้ตัวอย่างไร
Will you relinquish your military power
หรือว่าเพื่อความบริสุทธิ์แล้ว
to prove your innocence?
จะสละอำนาจทหาร
Then who's going to protect the great imperial grandson after that?
อย่างนั้นใครจะปกป้องพระนัดดารัชทายาทอีก
Even if you can bring the great imperial grandson
ต่อให้ท่านพาพระนัดดารัชทายาท
back to Laolan Pass,
กลับถึงด่านเหลาหลันได้
your simple-minded father
แต่เสด็จพ่อที่เลอะเลือนของท่าน
may order you to take your own life
หลังถูกคนยุยงแล้วมีราชโองการ
after being instigated by others.
สั่งให้ท่านฆ่าตัวตาย
Will you comply
ถึงเวลาท่านจะทำตามราชโองการ
or rebel when that time comes?
หรือไม่ทำตามล่ะ
When you are in a desperate situation,
รอท่านถึงทางตัน
how will you protect the great imperial grandson?
แล้วจะปกป้องพระนัดดารัชทายาทได้อย่างไร
Shiqi,
สือชีหลาง
I've already calculated
กลหมากเหนือเมฆตานี้
every move for you
ข้าคำนวณให้ท่าน
in this complex situation.
ทุกทางแล้ว
They are all dead ends.
มีแต่ทางตัน
Entering the Eastern Palace
มีเพียงท่าน เข้าเป็นเจ้าตำหนักบูรพาเสียเอง
is your only escape.
ท่านถึงมีทางรอด
I refuse to believe that this is my only way out.
ข้าไม่เชื่อ
Can you not always see human nature as so treacherous?
เจ้าอย่าคิดถึงใจคน
Over time,
อย่างนั้นผ่านไปสักพัก
you will find out for yourself
ท่านอ๋องก็อาจพบด้วยตัวเอง
how complex and treacherous
ว่าใจคนซับซ้อนขนาดไหน
human hearts can be.
ชั่วร้ายขนาดไหนกันแน่
So, did you ask me here
ดังนั้นที่เจ้านัดข้ามาวันนี้
just to tell me all this?
ก็เพื่อบอกเรื่องพวกนี้กับข้า
Yes.
ถูกต้อง
Do you like me?
เจ้าชอบข้าไหม
One day,
มีวันหนึ่ง
I encountered someone.
ข้าได้พบคนคนหนึ่ง
He's exceptionally talented
เขาเก่งมาก
and intelligent.
และฉลาดมากด้วย
He's unlike anyone
ข้าไม่เคยพบ
I've met before.
คนเช่นนี้มาก่อน
The first time meeting,
แม้พบกันครั้งแรก
we had a tough fight.
เราก็สู้กันอุตลุด
When we met the second time,
พบกันครั้งที่สอง
I kicked him into a well.
ข้าก็ถีบเขาลงบ่อ
But at that moment,
แต่ตอนนั้น
I knew
ข้าก็รู้ว่า
I liked him.
ข้าชอบเขา
Even though
แม้
I've never liked anyone before
ข้าไม่เคย
or know
แล้วก็ไม่รู้ว่าการชอบคนอื่น
what it feels like,
รสชาติเป็นอย่างไรกันแน่
I'm certain
แต่ในใจข้าแน่ใจมาก
I like him.
ว่าข้าชอบเขา
Whether he's Shiqi from Laolan Pass
ไม่ว่า
or Lord Qin,
หรือเป็นอ๋องฉิน
whether he's a commoner, the imperial grandson, or the crown prince,
ไม่ว่าเขาเป็นพ่อค้าหรือลูกกะจ๊อก
I just like him as a person.
ข้าก็แค่ชอบเขาเท่านั้น
You like me
เจ้าชอบข้า
and I like you too.
ข้าก็ชอบเจ้า
Why can't you marry me?
อย่างนั้นเหตุใดแต่งงานกับข้าไม่ได้
Please go back, Your Highness.
ท่านอ๋องกลับไปเถอะ
Perhaps after some time,
บางทีผ่านไปสักพัก
you'll understand
ท่านอ๋องก็จะเข้าใจ
that it's not about Lord Qin
ไม่ใช่อ๋องฉินอยากกลับด่านเหลาหลัน
wanting to return
เป็นสือชีหลาง
to Laolan Pass
ก็กลับด่านเหลาหลัน
and live as Shiqi.
เป็นสือชีหลางได้
But it's just that Lord Qin
แต่อ๋องฉิน
cannot avoid becoming the crown prince at the Eastern Palace.
ไม่เป็นองค์รัชทายาทตำหนักบูรพาไม่ได้
If I refused to be the crown prince,
ถ้าข้าไม่เป็นรัชทายาท
would you refuse to marry me?
เจ้าก็ไม่เต็มใจแต่งกับข้า
If I say yes,
ถ้าข้าบอกว่าใช่ล่ะ
would it make you feel better, Your Highness?
ในใจท่านอ๋อง
If Mister Shiqi marries Miss Cui,
สือชีหลางถ้าแต่งงานกับคุณหนูชุย
then she'll stay in the capital.
ก็จะอยู่ที่เมืองหลวง
in the capital, right?
อย่างนั้นเจ้าก็น่าจะ
Well, that's not certain.
ไม่แน่หรอก
Why not?
ทำไมถึงไม่แน่ล่ะ
If Miss Cui already stays in the capital,
คุณหนูชุยก็อยู่เมืองหลวงแล้ว
where else can you go?
เจ้ายังไปไหนได้อีก
Maybe
บางที
our Great General
แม่ทัพใหญ่เรา
won't agree to marry our young lady to Lord Qin.
อาจไม่ยอมยกคุณหนูเรา
That's impossible.
เป็นไปไม่ได้
Your Great General
แม่ทัพใหญ่ของเจ้า
already submitted a memorial
ถวายฎีกาแล้วไม่ใช่หรือ
to let Miss Cui choose her husband.
ให้คุณหนูชุย
Isn't it obvious
แบบนี้ยังไม่ชัดอีกหรือ
that she'll choose Mister Shiqi
นางต้องเลือกสือชีหลาง
as her husband?
มาเป็นเขยแน่
Moreover, they agreed to meet today,
อีกอย่างวันนี้พวกเขานัดพบกัน
probably to discuss the wedding.
ก็เพื่อปรึกษาเรื่องแต่งงานไม่ใช่หรือ
You're weird.
แปลกจริง
What does my young lady
คุณหนูข้า
and Lord Qin's wedding discussion
กับอ๋องฉินของเจ้าปรึกษาเรื่องแต่งงาน
have anything to do with us?
นี่เกี่ยวอะไรกับเราสองคนด้วย
Taozi.
เถาจื่อ
What?
ทำไม
I like you.
ข้าชอบเจ้า
I want to be with you all the time.
ข้าอยากอยู่กับเจ้าตลอดไป
Are...
เจ้า
Are you willing to?
เจ้าเต็มใจไหม
Well...
ข้าหรือ
What happened?
เกิดอะไรขึ้นเนี่ย
Why is Lord Qin
อ๋องฉินของเจ้า
suddenly leaving on his horse?
ทำไมจู่ ๆ ก็ขี่ม้าจากไป
My young lady is still there.
คุณหนูยังอยู่ตรงนั้นนะ
♪Waiting for memories to shatter and sink♪
♪รอความทรงจำ แหลกละเอียดจมหาย♪
Young Lady,
คุณหนู
what exactly
เมื่อครู่ท่านกับอ๋องฉิน
did you tell Lord Qin just now?
คุยอะไรกันแน่เจ้าคะ
Why did you suddenly leave on bad terms?
ทำไมจู่ ๆ ก็ จากกันไม่ดีล่ะ
What does that mean?
หมายความว่าอะไร
Didn't he come here to discuss the betrothal?
เขามาหาท่าน
What happened?
ทำไม
Don't tell me
หรือว่า
he doesn't want to marry you anymore.
เขาไม่อยากแต่งงานกับท่าน
He's just not willing to be the crown prince.
เขาแค่ไม่ยอมเป็นรัชทายาทเท่านั้น
But he doesn't understand
แต่เขาไม่เข้าใจ
that if he doesn't become the crown prince,
ถ้าเขาไม่เป็นรัชทายาท
he might not be able
แม้แต่ชีวิตตัวเอง
to save even his own life.
เขาก็อาจ
How can he marry me?
แล้วจะแต่งกับข้าได้อย่างไร
What's wrong with him?
คนคนนี้มันอย่างไรกัน
He clearly likes you so much,
ทั้ง ๆ ที่ชอบท่านขนาดนั้น
to the extent of giving up his own life.
ชอบถึงขั้นแม้แต่ชีวิตตัวเอง
Is it harder for him
นี่ หรือว่า
to be the crown prince than to lose his life?
ให้เขาเป็นรัชทายาท
♪If love remembers the promise I made to you♪
♪หากความรักจำได้ สัญญาที่รักษาเพื่อเจ้า♪
♪Despite going against fate, I have no regrets loving you♪
♪พลิกผันเหตุและผล ไม่เสียใจที่ยืนหยัดรักเพื่อเจ้า♪
Look.
♪ยอมตัดความปรารถนาเพื่อเจ้า♪
There are natural orders to follow, and hardships are relentless.
สี่ฤดูเป็นไปตามลำดับ ลมฝนไร้รัก
It's getting dark,
ฟ้าจะมืดแล้ว
and it's raining now, of all time.
ฝนดันตกลงมาอีก
How difficult it must be
คนเดินทาง
for those traveling on this path.
จะลำบากขนาดไหนกัน
♪Even if this love hurts me, I'll continue living for you♪
♪ต่อให้รักนี้ทำร้ายข้า ก็จะมีชีวิตอยู่เพื่อเจ้า♪
♪Holding onto the memories♪
♪ไปตามเค้าโครงในความทรงจำ♪
♪Waiting is my persistence♪
♪รอคอยคนที่ข้ายึดติด♪
♪If love remembers the promise I made to you♪
♪หากความรักจำได้ สัญญาที่รักษาเพื่อเจ้า♪
♪Despite going against fate, I have no regrets loving you♪
♪พลิกผันเหตุและผล ไม่เสียใจที่ยืนหยัดรักเพื่อเจ้า♪
Isn't that Lord Qin?
นั่นอ๋องฉินไม่ใช่หรือ
It's so early in the morning.
ยังเช้าอยู่เลย
Why is he rushing back from outside the city?
ทำไมท่านอ๋องถึงควบม้ามาจากนอกเมืองล่ะ
He seems a little distraught.
ท่านอ๋อง
I wonder what happened.
ไม่รู้ว่าเกิดอะไรขึ้น
Your Highness!
ท่านอ๋อง
Something happened at Lord Xin's residence.
จวนอ๋องซิ่นเกิดเรื่องแล้ว
What happened?
มีอะไร
There was a fire at Lord Xin's residence last night.
จวนอ๋องซิ่นเมื่อคืนไฟไหม้
Consort Xin has passed away.
ชายาอ๋องซิ่น สิ้นแล้ว
What?
อะไรนะ
Is this true?
เรื่องนี้จริงหรือ
It's absolutely true.
จริงแท้แน่นอน
No wonder
มิน่า
there was a sudden fire at Lord Xin's residence last night.
จวนอ๋องซิ่นถึงจู่ ๆ ก็ไฟไหม้
My poor sister-in-law,
พี่สะใภ้ที่น่าสงสารของข้า
along with all the maids and servants
รวมทั้งสาวใช้ บ่าวไพร่ทั้งหมด
failed to escape.
หนีออกมาไม่ได้สักคน
All of them perished in the flames.
ตายในกองเพลิงหมด
It turns out someone deliberately set fire.
ที่แท้มีคนจงใจวางเพลิง
Our spy at Lord Xin's residence saw
สายของเรา
that no one escaped,
เห็นไม่มีคนหนีออกมาได้สักคน
which made him suspicious.
รู้สึกเรื่องนี้มีเลศนัย
So, it took some effort
เขาเสียเวลาพักใหญ่
to investigate the matter.
ถึงสืบได้
Something seems to be amiss
เรือนของพระชายา
at the Consort Xin's courtyard.
ดูเหมือนผิดปกตินิดหน่อย
It also took some time
การดับเพลิงในวันนั้น
for people to put out the fire.
ก็ล่าช้าด้วย
This incident
เรื่องนี้
was certainly arson,
ต้องจงใจวางเพลิงแน่
not an accidental fire.
ไม่ใช่ไฟไหม้โดยอุบัติเหตุแน่นอน
We just don't know
เพียงแต่ไม่รู้ว่า
who did it.
เป็นฝีมือใคร
I never expected
คิดไม่ถึงจริง ๆ
the vast courtyard
ด้านหลังจวนอ๋องซิ่น
behind Lord Xin's Residence
เรือนทั้งแถบใหญ่ขนาดนี้
would be burnt to ashes.
จะถูกเผาราบหมด
The Consort Xin
พระชายากับ
didn't manage to escape.
หนีออกมาไม่ได้สักคน
Something's not right.
ไม่ถูก
What's not right?
อะไรไม่ถูก
A lord's residence has regulations.
จวนอ๋องมีกฎเกณฑ์
Lord Xin's Residence
จวนอ๋องซิ่นบูรณะจาก
was renovated from the former Lord Jin's Residence.
จวนเก่าของจวนอ๋องจิ้นผู้เฒ่า
The pillars were made of precious golden nanmu wood.
คานและเสาใช้ไม้หนานมู่เนื้อทองทั้งหมด
It's very sturdy.
เนื้อไม้แข็งมาก
Even the golden nanmu wood turned into charcoal.
แม้แต่ไม้หนานมู่เนื้อทอง
But the bricks on the nearby courtyard wall
อิฐของกำแพงเรือนข้าง ๆ
are not charred.
กลับไม่เป็นรอยดำเลยสักนิด
It also rained last night.
เมื่อคืนยังฝนตกอีก
Yet, they couldn't put out the fire in time.
จวนอ๋องซิ่นกลับดับไฟไม่ทัน
None of this adds up.
แต่ละเรื่อง ล้วนไม่ถูก
Shiqi,
สือชีหลาง
do you mean...
ท่านหมายความว่า
It must be arson
ต้องเป็นการวางเพลิงแน่
or someone poured oil
ไม่ก็ราดน้ำมัน
or used some kind of inflammable substance.
ไม่ก็ใช้ของช่วยในการเผาไหม้
Otherwise, even the golden nanmu wood
ไม่อย่างนั้นเป็นไปไม่ได้
can't turn into charcoal in such a short time.
ในเวลาสั้น ๆ เช่นนี้
Since it's arson,
ในเมื่อเป็นการวางเพลิง
Sister-in-law's death
อย่างนั้นการตายของพี่สะใภ้ใหญ่
has hidden motives.
ก็ต้องมีลับลมคมใน
Who could set fire to Consort Xin's backyard
สามารถวางเพลิงที่เรือนหลังของพระชายา
and control the servants?
อีกทั้งควบคุมบ่าวไพร่ได้
Coincidentally,
บังเอิญ
I asked Jun to help me
สองวันก่อนข้ายังไปขอร้องพี่ใหญ่
regarding the betrothal with Miss Cui a few days ago.
ให้เขาช่วยข้าสู่ขอบุตรีสกุลชุย
Who else could it be?
จะเป็นใครไปได้
Are you suggesting
ท่านอ๋องหมายถึง
that Lord Xin is behind this?
เรื่องนี้เป็นฝีมืออ๋องซิ่น
My elder brother dared
พี่ใหญ่ข้าคนนี้ถึงกับกล้าเผา
to burn his own wife to death.
ภรรยาหลวงตัวเอง
Clearly, he's targeting
เห็นชัดว่าเขาก็พุ่งเป้ามาที่
Cui Yi's proposal to choose a son-in-law.
เรื่องชุยอี่ถวายฎีกาเลือกเขยเหมือนกัน
In that case,
เมื่อเป็นเช่นนี้
he must also want to fight
เขาก็ต้องแย่ง
for Miss Cui
บุตรีสกุลชุยคนนี้ด้วยแน่
and won't help me anymore.
ไม่ช่วยข้าแล้ว
Your Highness,
ท่านอ๋อง
isn't this our chance?
นี่คือโอกาสของเราไม่ใช่หรือ
You're right.
เจ้าพูดถูก
If Father finds out,
ถ้าให้เสด็จพ่อรู้เข้าละก็
Jun won't be able to marry Miss Cui.
พี่ใหญ่ก็สู่ขอบุตรีสกุลชุยไม่ได้
My chances of winning will be even greater.
โอกาสชนะของข้าก็ยิ่งมาก
Your Highness, you're wise indeed.
ท่านอ๋องปราดเปรื่อง
I believe in a few days,
ข้าเชื่อว่าอีกสองวัน
Ni will also become suspicious of this matter.
น้องสามก็ต้องสงสัยเรื่องนี้
By then, I must lend him
ถึงเวลาข้าต้องช่วย
a helping hand.
น้องสามคนนี้ของข้าดี ๆ ซะหน่อย
After all, his feelings for sister-in-law
อย่างไรเสียตอนนั้น
were the deepest back in the day, and he admired her the most.
ก็ลึกล้ำที่สุด
If he finds out
ถ้าให้เขารู้ว่า
Jun is responsible for sister-in-law's death,
พี่ใหญ่เป็นคนฆ่าพี่สะใภ้ใหญ่ละก็
he'll surely report it to Father.
เขาจะต้องทูลเสด็จพ่อแน่
Then, Father will conduct a thorough investigation.
เสด็จพ่อก็จะต้องตรวจสอบถึงที่สุด
By then, Jun
ถึงเวลาพี่ใหญ่ข้า
will be in big trouble.
ก็ซวยแล้ว
Lord Xin is really ruthless.
อ๋องซิ่นคนนี้อำมหิตมาก
Do you think
เจ้าคิดว่า
it's Lord Xin's doing?
เป็นฝีมืออ๋องซิ่น
Who else could it be but him?
นอกจากเขายังเป็นใครไปได้อีก
I never expected him
คิดไม่ถึงจริง ๆ
to kill his own wife.
ว่าเขาจะฆ่า
That's the imperial family.
นั่นคือราชวงศ์นะ
Family members harming each other,
พ่อลูกฆ่ากัน
siblings killing each other.
พี่น้องห้ำหั่นกัน
Even if he killed his wife,
ต่อให้ฆ่าภรรยาหลวง
it's not something new.
ก็ไม่ใช่เรื่องแปลกใหม่อะไร
Father,
ท่านพ่อ
I want to go to Xichang.
ข้าอยากไปเมืองซีฉาง
What do you want to do in Xichang?
เจ้าจะไปเมืองซีฉางทำอะไร
Lord Xin killed his wife
อ๋องซิ่นฆ่าภรรยาหลวง
just to marry me.
ก็เพราะอยากแต่งงานกับข้า
I want to see
อย่างนั้นข้าจะดูว่า
how he will fight
เขากับอ๋องฉี
with Lord Qi.
จะแย่งกันอย่างไร
You actually want to see
ที่จริงเจ้าอยากดู
how Lord Qin will react, right?
อ๋องฉินจะทำอย่างไรมากกว่ากระมัง
Young Lady,
คุณหนู
are we visiting nanny of Lord Qin today?
วันนี้เรา
Cui Yi submitted a memorial,
ชุยอี่ถวายฎีกา
wanting to choose a son-in-law among the princes.
จะเลือกเขย
This memorial
ฎีกาเล่มนี้
is quite strange.
แปลกประหลาดมาก
What's strange about it?
ประหลาดตรงไหนเจ้าคะ
I once saw
ข้าเคยเห็น
the original text of this memorial.
ต้นฉบับที่คัดลอกจากฎีกาเล่มนี้
If Cui Yi submitted it
ชุยอี่ถวายฎีกา
to marry his daughter to Lord Qin,
เพราะอยากยกบุตรีให้แต่งกับอ๋องฉิน
he would undoubtedly use different wordings,
อย่างนั้นจะต้องเขียนอีกแบบหนึ่ง
and there could be subtle hints in the text.
ในตัวอักษร
But there weren't any.
แต่ดันไม่มี
If Cui Yi didn't submit the memorial
หากชุยอี่ถวายฎีกาเล่มนี้
to marry his daughter to Lord Qin,
ไม่ใช่เพราะอยากยกบุตรีให้แต่งกับอ๋องฉิน
there might have been
อย่างนั้นในนี้
another plan behind it.
ก็อาจมีแผนการอื่น
So that's why you're going
ดังนั้นวันนี้คุณหนู
to Lord Qin's residence today.
ถึงจะไปจวนอ๋องฉิน
This morning, I saw Lord Qin entering the city,
เช้านี้เห็นอ๋องฉินเข้าเมือง
seemingly soaked from a night of rain.
เหมือนตากฝนมาทั้งคืน
He's usually a carefree person,
คนที่เปี่ยมไปด้วยพลังอิสระอย่างเขา
and almost never had such
แทบไม่เคยมี
an appearance.
สภาพเช่นนี้มาก่อน
I think
คิดว่า
he must have encountered an unexpected turn of events.
คงเจอกับการเปลี่ยนแปลงอย่างใหญ่หลวง
And this may be related
การเปลี่ยนแปลงนี้
to the memorial
อาจเกี่ยวข้องกับ
the Cui family submitted.
ฎีกาที่สกุลชุยถวาย
♪If I forget the fleeting of time♪
♪หากลืมแสงหิ่งห้อยที่หายวับไป♪
♪Waiting for memories♪
♪รอความทรงจำ♪
♪To shatter and sink♪
♪แหลกละเอียดจมหาย♪
♪The emotional scars in your heart♪
♪ตกลงบนรอยด่างบนหัวใจเจ้า♪
♪Are the entanglement♪
♪ความเกี่ยวพันนั้น♪
♪I find hard to let go of♪
♪คือสิ่งที่ข้ายากจะตัดใจ♪
♪If longing is not forgotten♪
♪หากความคะนึงหาไม่เคยจางหาย♪
♪I long to return to the very first moment♪
♪กลับไปสู่เวลาแรกด้วยความอาลัย♪
♪The affection we had in our fateful situation♪
♪ความอบอุ่นที่โชคชะตาเคยมี♪
♪How I wish to keep it for you♪
♪อยากเก็บไว้เพื่อเจ้า♪
♪If love still remembers♪
♪หากความรักจำได้♪
♪The promises we made♪
♪เราเคยสัญญา♪
♪Even if this love hurts me♪
♪ต่อให้รักนี้ทำร้ายข้า♪
♪I'll continue living for you♪
♪ก็จะมีชีวิตอยู่เพื่อเจ้า♪
♪Holding onto the memories♪
♪ไปตามเค้าโครงในความทรงจำ♪
♪Waiting is my persistence♪
♪รอคอยคนที่ข้ายึดติด♪
♪If love remembers♪
♪หากความรักจำได้♪
♪The promise I made to you♪
♪สัญญาที่รักษาเพื่อเจ้า♪
♪Despite going against fate♪
♪พลิกผันเหตุและผล♪
♪I have no regrets loving you♪
♪ไม่เสียใจที่ยืนหยัดรักเพื่อเจ้า♪
♪I'm willing to sacrifice for you♪
♪ยอมตัดความปรารถนาเพื่อเจ้า♪
♪As I wait for your answer♪
♪รอเจ้าตอบข้าเสมอ♪
♪If love remembers♪
♪หากความรักจำได้♪
♪The promise I made to you♪
♪สัญญาที่รักษาเพื่อเจ้า♪
♪Despite going against fate♪
♪พลิกผันเหตุและผล♪
♪I have no regrets loving you♪
♪ไม่เสียใจที่ยืนหยัดรักเพื่อเจ้า♪
♪I'm willing to sacrifice for you♪
♪ยอมตัดความปรารถนาเพื่อเจ้า♪
♪As I wait for your answer♪
♪รอเจ้าตอบข้าเสมอ♪